<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>APAD on Wenxuan Zhao</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/en/tags/apad/</link>
    <description>Recent content in APAD on Wenxuan Zhao</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Nov 2023 20:07:32 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/en/tags/apad/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The within-the-bar bias</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/2023/11/the-within-the-bar-bias/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Nov 2023 20:07:32 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/2023/11/the-within-the-bar-bias/</guid>
      <description>A paper A day: Newman and Scholl discovered a cognitive asymmetry called the with-in-the-bar bias originated from the graphical asymmetry in the bar graph representation of mean.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>Broadly, the paper focus on how bar graphs are <em>naturally</em> interpreted.</p>
<p>The mean value, a symmetric value that is influenced to the same degree by values that are located at equal distances above and below the mean, is represented by the farthest edge of a bar that originates from one particular axis, most typically below the mean.</p>
<p>Visual objects are defined by the closure of their boundaries, such that attention is attracted to such objects but does not flow beyond the boundaries.</p>
<p>==&gt; Hypothesis:
When viewers are shown a bar graph that depicts a mean and are then asked to judge the likelihood that a particular value was part of its underlying distribution, they will judge points that fall with-in the bar as being more likely than points equidistant from the mean, but outside the bar.
- they reflexively attend to the bars, and so to mistakenly prioritize regions within the bars over equivalent regions outside the bars</p>
<h2 id="experiment-1-typical-bar-graph-with-error-bar">Experiment 1: typical bar graph with error bar</h2>
<h3 id="design">Design</h3>
<ol>
<li>The participants were first shown a vertical bar graph with two bars originating from the lower x-axis
<ul>
<li>half saw this: <img loading="lazy" src="within_condition.png" alt="within-condition"  />
</li>
<li>The other half saw this: <img loading="lazy" src="outside_condition.png" alt="outside-condition"  />
</li>
<li>The actual means were the same, the y-axis (and in turn the bar height) is different between subjects.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Some filler items.</li>
<li>Participants were then presented with a new page with the same graph axes as they just saw(remember, in step 1, the y-axis is different between 2 conditions) and a single test point, drawn at the midpoint of the y-axis. They then were asked to judge the likelihood from 1-9 that this value was part of the distribution that had been depicted by the bar seen earlier.
<ul>
<li>this graph will be shown to participants who saw the overall &ldquo;higher&rdquo; bars: the within-condition group: <img loading="lazy" src="within_test.png" alt="within-condition"  />
</li>
<li>the outside-bar group would see this: <img loading="lazy" src="outside_test.png" alt="outside-condition"  />
</li>
<li>the test point stays at the midline across all conditions. The western and the eastern, as well as whether the test point was within or outside of the bar are balanced between subjects.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="results">Results</h3>
<p>Although the test point was equidistant from the initially depicted means, it was judged to be more likely to have come from the distribution when it was below the mean than when it was above the mean.</p>
<h2 id="experiment-2">Experiment 2</h2>
<p>A potential confounding variable in experiment 1 is that the systematic differences in behavior between conditions may also due to viewers have a more general bias to favor points that are numerically below the mean.</p>
<p>To deconfound that, two additional y-axis sets of labels that represent the two types of &ldquo;falling&rdquo; bars were introduced. In total we have four conditions: rising-&ldquo;short&rdquo; bar, rising-&ldquo;long&rdquo; bar (short and long share the same numerical mean, one is short and one is long b/c of the manipulated y-axis labels), falling-&ldquo;short&rdquo; bar, and falling-&ldquo;long&rdquo; bar. Since the testing point is the same across conditions, participants who saw short bar are in &ldquo;outside-bar&rdquo; conditions, the same as what is in experiment 1. The catch is that the testing point will fall outside of the bars <em>and</em> below the mean in the falling-short condition.</p>
<h3 id="result">Result</h3>
<p>Test points that originated from within the bar again produced greater likelihood ratings, and it held for <em>both</em> rising bars and falling bars.</p>
<h2 id="experiment-3">Experiment 3</h2>
<p>A second alternative explanation could be that participants assigned higher likelihood values to less extreme numeric labels. In experiment 1 and 2, the within- the-bar points had less extreme numeric labels than did the outside-the-bar points.</p>
<h3 id="method">Method</h3>
<p>This experiment differed from the previous studies in the following ways:</p>
<ul>
<li>The y-axis labels were identical across all conditions;</li>
<li>The graphs contained only a single bar with no error bar (to minimize memory load);</li>
<li>The graph depicted a new hypothetical source of the data (freezing points of chemicals in a science class) that was amenable to both positive and negative numbers centered at zero.</li>
</ul>
<p>In all conditions the bar depicted a mean of zero, and y-axis are the same. Therefore, the 4 conditions are:</p>
<ul>
<li>falling bar, 5 (inside - not extreme)</li>
<li>falling bar, -5 (outside, extreme)</li>
<li>rising bar, 5 (outside, not extreme)</li>
<li>rising bar, -5 (inside, extreme)
I am not sure if -5 should be seen as the &ldquo;extreme&rdquo; value, compared to 5, or I am understanding incorrectly here.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="result-1">Result</h3>
<p>In both rising bar and falling bar conditions, points within the bars were judeged significantly more likely to belong to the distribution.</p>
<h2 id="experiement-4-bar-stays-when-making-the-judgement">Experiement 4: bar stays when making the judgement</h2>
<p>They wonder if in the &ldquo;free viewing&rdquo; condition the effect is still there: they made the graph was still present when they asked participants for their judgements. The rest of the setup is the same as that of experiment 3.</p>
<p>The effect is still here.</p>
<h2 id="experiment-5">Experiment 5:</h2>
<p>They changed the between-subject design to <em>within-subject</em>. They counterbalanced the question order and maybe also the rising, falling order.
The rest stays the same as experiment 4.
<img loading="lazy" src="e5within.png" alt=""  />
</p>
<h3 id="result-2">Result</h3>
<p>The effect is still significant: though 73% of the participants did rate the points as equally likely,
the other 27% of participants reliably favor with-in-bar points.</p>
<h2 id="experiment-6-effect-on-downstream-decisions">Experiment 6: effect on downstream decisions</h2>
<h3 id="design-1">Design</h3>
<p>A between-subject design? with 3 groups:</p>
<ul>
<li>control group: no graph shown, were given the same scenario as the other 2 conditions and were asked for a decision using a sliding bar (if the new tires should increase BTS ot decrease the BTS).</li>
<li>rising bar group: the bar rises from -200 to 0 and stops at 0 to represent the mean.</li>
<li>falling bar group: the bar falls from 200 t0 0 and stops at 0 to represent the mean.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="result-3">Result</h3>
<p>The presence of a rising bar led participants significantly increase BTS levels relative to control, while a falling bar caused participants to significantly decrease BTS levels relative to control.
A further comparison confirmed that the resulting BTS levels differed between the rising- and falling-bar graph conditions.</p>
<h3 id="discussion">Discussion</h3>
<p>This confirms that the influence of the within-the-bar bias is not limited to reasoning about bar graphs and statistical distributions per se, but can also influence decisions made about the content that the bar graphs depict.</p>
<h2 id="discussion-of-the-results">Discussion of the results</h2>
<p>Bar graphs of means will doubtless remain ubiquitous, but in some situations means might be better represented with points rather than asymmetric bars—or, where possible, with depictions of the <em>distributions themselves</em>.</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://static-content.springer.com/esm/art%3A10.3758%2Fs13423-012-0247-5/MediaObjects/13423_2012_247_MOESM1_ESM.pdf">The stimuli and instructions can be found at here.</a></strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Perceptual proxies for extracting averages in data visualizations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/2023/11/perceptual-proxies-for-extracting-averages-in-data-visualizations/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2023 12:42:22 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/2023/11/perceptual-proxies-for-extracting-averages-in-data-visualizations/</guid>
      <description>A paper a day: Yuan et al showed that when comparing averages across multiple data points, viewers use surprisingly primitive perceptual cues: the hierarchy of precision for perceptual encodings of data doesn&amp;rsquo;t hold for comparison of averages of even pairs of data.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="intro">Intro</h2>
<p>The power of visualizations is constrained by the limitations and idiosyncrasies of the human visual system.
- this is how they use the word &ldquo;constraints&rdquo;</p>
<p>One of the findings based on constraints is a hierarchy of judgment precision among visual features that encode data values
- eg. spatial position encoding (eg. compare length on the common ground) &gt; length (stacked bar chart) &gt; area (treemap).</p>
<p>The catch: The precision of these encodings was determined for comparisons between <em>single</em> values, under the assumption that what is true for comparing single values is also true for multiple values.
- researchers therefore often decompose graph reading into elementary perceptual processes.</p>
<p>There hypothesis is that the advantage of position encoding is not availble for comparisons involving larger sets: the visual system fails to use the most precise feature (position) and uses a less precise feature (length or even the area of the bars), because it may not be able to extract averages from multiple bar values; it may be restricted (or at least, irresistibly tempted) to considering sums only.</p>
<h2 id="experiment-1">Experiment 1</h2>
<h3 id="stimuli">Stimuli</h3>
<p>Task: Participants judged which one of two variables had a higher value (1vs1) or higher mean (2vs2 and 6vs6).</p>
<p>Three types of comparisons: 1 vs 1, 2 vs 2, and 6 vs 6.</p>
<p>Three graph types: dot plots (position only), bar graph (position and spaial extent (length and area)), and misaligned bar graph (spaital extent only).</p>
<p>This graph shows the stimuli usign in both experiments:
<img loading="lazy" src="fig3.png" alt="Fig3"  />
</p>
<h3 id="design">Design</h3>
<p>They used a 3 by 3 (3 comparison type by 3 graph type) with-in subject design to measure just noticeable differences (JND) using a staircase procedure.
- A small JND means a participant can detect a small difference between two groups, reflecting higher perceptual discriminability.
- During the staircase procedure, if participants correctly (or incorrectly) answered the previous trial, the difficulty (defined by the difference between the means of the y-axis values of each group) of the next trial increased (or decreased) by one level.
- 12 levels of staircase.
- The &ldquo;ceiling&rdquo; of the staircase could be determined by simulating random guess. People should do better than random guess.
- A separate staircase was run for each of the nine conditions.</p>
<p>They also did several manipulations in generating stimuli to rule out the possibility that participants used statistical information other than the mean in their judgment.
- for 6vs6, for example, they randomized which set had the larger mean with which set had the larger standard deviation, largest single value, and smallest single value.</p>
<p>The nine unique conditions were randomly presented in each block of nine trials. Each block was followed by a break that the participant could end by pressing a key. A new block of trials was then be shown in a random order, and these blocks continued until the end of the experiment. Once the 1vs1 conditions were complete, only 2vs2 and 6vs6 trials were shown.</p>
<h3 id="procedure">Procedure</h3>
<p>Participants were introduced to the experiment as a graph-reading task. They were told that the y-axis represented the time it took for a red and a blue team to finish a car racing game. Sometimes there was only one car within each team; sometimes there were multiple cars. Participants were told to judge which team on average took longer. For the misaligned bar graph condition, they were told explicitly that the length of the bars represented the time values.</p>
<p>For each trial: a fixation (500ms) + a left-right judgement on which side has higher average (2s, if no response after 2s, then marked incorrect and participants were reminded to response quicker).</p>
<p>([25 trials for 1vs1] + [49 trials for 2vs2] + [49 trials for 6vs6]) × [3 graph types] = 369 trials plus a set of two practice trials.
- why such imbalance</p>
<h3 id="results">Results</h3>
<p>To prove their hypothsis, they are able to find a significant interaction between comparison type and graph type: in 1vs1, the average JND differnece of misaligned bar graph is significantly higher than the other two.
- These results indicate that participants had relied on the spatial position information when comparing individual values on normal bar graphs.</p>
<p>In contrast, for 2vs2 comparison, performance on the dot graphs was marginally significantly worse than on the normal bar graphs, but there was no significant performance difference between the normal bar graphs and the misaligned bar graphs. For 6vs6 comparisons, there was no significant difference among conditions.</p>
<p>The ANOVA analysis also revealed a main effect of comparison type: comparisons between single values significantly better than 2vs2, which were significantly better than 6vs6. They did not find a main effect of graph type.</p>
<h3 id="discussion">Discussion</h3>
<p>In 1vs1, participants relied on the spatial position.
In 2vs2 (pair comparison), participants had relied on the spatial extent of the bars rather than their spatial position in bar and misaligned bar graph conditions.
For 6vs6 (mutivalue comparison), it is possible that participants treat entire set of bars as a single unit, summing the area of its shape envelope instead of the averaging the length of its bars. If so, this strategy should suffer for displays with an unequal number of bars between the groups. Thus, here comes the 2nd experiment.</p>
<h2 id="experiment-2">Experiment 2</h2>
<h3 id="stimuli-1">Stimuli</h3>
<p>2 new comparison types: 10vs10 and 6vs10. They also added small set size conditions (1vs1 and 2vs2) and used them as base-line measures to exclude outliers (whoever could not perform these baseline conditions within 3 SD from mean is excluded).</p>
<h3 id="design-1">Design</h3>
<p>They used the staircase method with the three-down/one-up design: three correct answers in a row multiplied the staircase value by 0.75, and one incorrect answer multiplied the staircase value by 1.11.
- These constants yielded a staircase that would converge on a JND equivalent to 68% accuracy.</p>
<p>The experiment comprised three blocks. In each block, 16 trials of one condition were presented consecutively. Following a break, this process was repeated until all conditions were seen. The second and third blocks were the same as the first, but the order of the conditions was randomized each time. The staircase of each condition in the second and third block was a continuation of the previous bock’s staircase. The experiment included a total of (5 set sizes) × (3 graph types) × (3 blocks) × (16 trials) = 720 trials per subject. Feedback was given for the first 16 trials for all conditions (the easiest part of the staircase) to ensure that subjects understood the task.</p>
<h3 id="results-1">Results</h3>
<p>Anova shows no significant effect for both set size and graph type and their interaction in 6vs6 and 10vs10 set size, so they combined these 2 into the <em>same set size</em> comparison condition and treated 6vs10 as the <em>different set size</em> comparison condition.</p>
<p>The ANOVA revealed a robust main effect between the forementioned two comparison types (same vs. different set size). The ANOVA did not detect a significant main effect of graph type.</p>
<p>When there was unequal numbers of items between groups (different set sizes), a planned comparison between dot graphs and the normal bar graphs indicates that performance was significantly better on the dot graphs than on the normal bar graphs.</p>
<h3 id="discussion-1">Discussion</h3>
<p>It is possible that, for the dots in the six versus ten condition, a center-of-mass proxy might be used for the dots, as opposed to a summed area proxy for the bars.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion--future-directions">Conclusion &amp; Future Directions</h2>
<p>The hierarchy of encoding precision of single-value comparisons (Cleveland &amp; McGill, 1984) is typically assumed to extrapolate to more complex displays. The present results suggest that it does not, and that multivalue comparisons can rely on surprisingly different perceptual proxies for the desired statistics.</p>
<p>Why did participants appear to rely on sums instead of averages? Their result is particularly surprising given the extensive evidence that the visual system can compute visual statistics across basic features. This incongruent result may provide a case of use-inspired basic research (Shneiderman, 2015), leading visual cognition researchers to find the limiting factors to such statistical extraction.</p>
<p>The visual system is biased to deal with whole objects, rather than the features or parts of the objects, When asked to track multiple moving objects, observers have extreme difficulty tracking just one end of a moving bar, reflexively snapping their attention to the whole bar instead, and a similar reflex may lead viewers to bias recall of values plotted in bar graphs toward the center of the bar, instead of the top edge (with-in-the-bar-bias). In the current study, although spatial position might be the most relevant feature on a bar graph for comparing the averages between groups of values, viewers seem to be incapable of ignoring the spatial extent (length or area) information, and select the whole bars as the unit of attention.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biased Average Position Estimates in Line and Bar Graphs</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/2023/11/biased-average-position-estimates-in-line-and-bar-graphs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Nov 2023 18:35:11 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/2023/11/biased-average-position-estimates-in-line-and-bar-graphs/</guid>
      <description>A paper a day: Xiong et al conducts experiments on estimating averages in line and bar graphs, in which they identified systematic perceptual biases.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>Preceptual psychology reveals that preception of visual information can be systematically influenced by/biased based on <strong>context</strong> and <strong>recent history</strong>. This is also true in data visualization.</p>
<p>Position in past literature is believed to be the most precise channel to encode information. In this paper, they will show systematica biases in perception of data using positional encodings.</p>
<h2 id="perceptual-biases">Perceptual Biases</h2>
<ul>
<li>lower-levels biases: size, features that include hue, brightness, orientation, and position perception</li>
<li>biases mechanisms: context (background, neighbor, categorical boundary, salient points), adaptation
<ul>
<li>Positions are encoded somewhat categorically (similar to color), so that changes to a category boundary are easier to detect, compared to equally distant changes that do not cross a category boundary.</li>
<li>The position memory of a briefly presented object can be biased by context or nearby salient points in the display. Memory for the position of an object can be biased toward the average position of an associated group of objects.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="cognitive-biases">Cognitive Biases</h2>
<ul>
<li>higher level biases: estimation, decision, judgement</li>
<li>biases mechanisms: recent history: <em>priming</em>, and context
<ul>
<li>anchoring effect: uncertain target estimates can be strongly biased by other provided values, even if they are objectively irrelevant.</li>
<li>Such higher-level cognitive influences may also affect pattern perception in data visualizations
<ul>
<li>slope estimate</li>
<li>judgments of class separability</li>
<li>eg. viewers who saw a high-intensity title recall a steeper slope than those who saw a low-intensity title</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="contributions">Contributions</h2>
<p>Previous work on investigating perceptual biases has focused on biases within visualizations in a higher-level, cognitive context.
- how do semantics of titles, axes, or other visualization elements, or priming influence perception.</p>
<p>This paper focus on potential biases found in lower-level perception of data — can people accurately perceive purely graphical information?
- possible biases within <strong>average position estimations</strong></p>
<h2 id="study-overview">Study Overview</h2>
<h3 id="stimuli-and-procedure">Stimuli and procedure</h3>
<p>The stimuli could appear at top and/or bottom. 3 means of height for both top and bottom: low, medium, high
- determined in pilot trial by two-alternative forced choice. Following conventions from psychophysics, an ideal distance between means would have participants accurately discriminating them in at least 75% of all trials: 12 pixels for line, 5 pixels for bar in a 140 pixel display frame with average viweing distance of 47 cm.</p>
<p>Procedure:</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="fig2.png" alt="fig2"  />
</p>
<p>Three experiments:</p>
<ol>
<li>One line or one set of bars: investigates whether systematic biases exist in position estimates for <em>simple graphs</em>, where a single line or a single set of bars is the only present, graphed data series.</li>
<li>two lines or two sets of bars: how average position perception of a graphed data series can be distorted in the presence of an <em>identical</em> type of data series.</li>
<li>one line and one set of bars: how the average perception of one type of data series can be distorted by a <em>different</em> type of data series</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="experiment-1">Experiment 1</h2>
<p>This experiment establishes a <strong>baseline</strong> to understand how a single graphed data series is perceived without the potential influence of other graphed data series. These findings will be later compared to how the presence of an additional graphed data series may further bias perception.</p>
<h3 id="design">Design</h3>
<ol>
<li>precue to cue the participant</li>
<li>stimulus conditions:
<ul>
<li>top vs bottom</li>
<li>noisy vs uniform</li>
<li>line vs bar depends on the precue</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>mask</li>
<li>use response probe to get the estimated position of lines from the participants.</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="analysis">Analysis</h3>
<p>They used a mixed-effect linear model.</p>
<h3 id="result">Result</h3>
<p>They observed an overall *<em>underestimation</em> of line position, in which participants estimated average line positions to be lower than where the average position of the line actually appeared. They also tested their hypothesis on participants&rsquo; heuristics and negated it: for noisy lines, participants did not base their average position estimations only on the lowest point for lines on both the top and bottom half of the display.</p>
<p>They observed an overall overestimation of bar position, where participants systematically estimated average bar positions to be higher than its actual position. They again excluded the possibility that the participants were simply averaging the highest and lowest points on the set of bars to generate their average positional estimates.</p>
<h2 id="experiment-2">Experiment 2</h2>
<h3 id="design-1">Design</h3>
<ol>
<li>preque participants to report the average position of a line or a set of bars presented at the top or bottom of the display.</li>
<li>stimulus:
<ul>
<li>line vs bar half half</li>
<li>judge the top vs bottom</li>
<li>all noisy</li>
<li>control trials: each participant estimated the average position of a single noisy line or a single noisy set of bars, replicating Experiment 1.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="result-1">Result</h3>
<p>They replicated the results in experiment 1 in the control trials. They also observed an underestimation in average line positions and an overestimation in average bar positions in &ldquo;compound&rdquo; (two lines or two sets of bars) displays.</p>
<p>Additionally, we also found an effect of “perceptual pull”: position estimates for a target data series (a set of bars or a line) were ‘pulled’ toward the irrelevant data series shown on the same graph: there was a significant interaction between location and display type
- participants underestimated the top line even more compared to single-line displays; underestimation of the bottom line was reduced.
- Overestimation of the top bars was reduced; overestimation of the bottom set of bars was exaggerated.</p>
<h2 id="experiment-3">Experiment 3</h2>
<h3 id="design-2">Design</h3>
<p>Similar to experiment 2 except with different graph types in the same display: compound bar-line and compound line-bar displays.</p>
<h3 id="result-2">Result</h3>
<p>Results from the first 2 are replicated, and the extent of perceptual pull does not depend on data series type.</p>
<h3 id="perceptual-pull-as-anchoring-effect">Perceptual pull as anchoring effect</h3>
<ul>
<li>Perceptual pull is exerted on a target data series when an irrelevant data series acts as a non-target baseline.</li>
<li>Similar to the cognitive anchoring effect, the observed perceptual pull was greater when the baseline series appeared to be farther away (high magnitude baseline).
<ul>
<li>I am not sure where this comes from?</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="future-direction">Future direction</h2>
<ul>
<li>Why underestimate average of line chart and overestimate average of bar charts
<ul>
<li>could the aspect ratio of bar charts explain?</li>
<li>figure-ground encoding: attention biases ground, and bars are grounds and will be overestimated, and the converse is true for line?</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>the root cause
<ul>
<li>might they be more cognitive and strategic, leaving more room for strategy interventions to mitigate the biases? Manipulating the viewer’s task could determine whether the bias stems from averaging ensemble positions, or is more generally a bias of perceiving even a single mark position.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>more complex stimuli</li>
<li>alternative response probe: the current probe may also pull the reponse via &ldquo;perceptual pulling&rdquo;.</li>
<li>test encodings other than position: underestimation and overestimation when perceive values encoded in size, orientation, saturation, etc.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="design-guidelines">Design guidelines</h2>
<ul>
<li>Position estimation biases were smaller and judgments were more precise for bars compared to lines =&gt; in the absence of other constraints, use bars.</li>
<li>Designers seeking the confidence of avoid- ing perceptual pull effects could avoid plotting two series in the same display.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="my-takeaways">My takeaways</h2>
<ol>
<li>Context and recent history are the two key dimensions that induce biases.</li>
<li>The experiments (including the pilot) are built up nicely: logically coherent and make it easy for analysis.</li>
<li>The perceptual pull phenomenon is interesting both in and of itself and in its correspondence to the anchoring effect.</li>
<li>The paper does not delve into why the biases it identifies happen, leaving room for future works.</li>
<li>The potential biase induced by response probe and small sample size may be the reason why there is conflicting result from other papers. For example: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chb.2016.01.036">Perception of bar graphs - A biased impression?</a> concludes from experiments that people tend to <em>underestimate</em> the average of a set of bars.</li>
</ol>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Philosophy of Art and Aesthetics, Psychology, and Neuroscience</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/2023/07/the-philosophy-of-art-and-aesthetics-psychology-and-neuroscience/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 10:08:48 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/2023/07/the-philosophy-of-art-and-aesthetics-psychology-and-neuroscience/</guid>
      <description>A Paper a Day: The Philosophy of Art and Aesthetics, Psychology, and Neuroscience: studies in literature, music, and visual arts by Noël Carroll, Margaret Moore, and William P. Seeley</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Alexander Baumgarten, 1735: Baumgarten used the phrase episteme aisthetike to mean the science of what is sensed and imagined, in contrast to the science of what is known through rational thought. In his incomplete Aesthetica, Baumgarten further defined the terms as follows: “Aesthetics (the theory of the liberal arts, the logic of the lower capacities of cognition [gnoseologia inferior], the art of thinking beautifully, the art of the analogon rationis) is the science of <strong>sensible cognition</strong>.” Since then, philosophers started exploring topics of:</p>
<ul>
<li>judgments of beauty: faculties of the judging subject and the qualities judged in the object</li>
<li>taste and preference</li>
<li>role of imagination</li>
<li>aesthetic and morality</li>
<li>experience of artwork</li>
</ul>
<p>only with the advent of <strong>cognitive science</strong> in the late 20th century that Baumgarten’s vision of aesthetics as a <em>science</em> of sensory cognition, including the study of our engagement with artworks, has become truly possible.</p>
<h2 id="the-viability-of-aesthetic-as-a-science">The Viability of Aesthetic as a Science</h2>
<ul>
<li>Logical Positivists: preferred to exclude anything that involves subjective feeling from the general domain of knowledge. Science could not, in principle, have any bearing on questions about the nature of art, beauty, or aesthetic appreciation.</li>
<li>analytic philosophers have been generally skeptical about the relevance of psychology to the philosophy of art and aesthetics.
<ul>
<li>Ludwig Wittgenstein’s Lectures in Aesthetics：</li>
<li>George Dickie’s “Is Psychology Relevant to Aesthetics”
<ul>
<li>when we answer aesthetic questions with data concerning the behavioral responses of participants to particular artworks we are committing a category mistake—we confuse a logical problem for a scientific one: what matters in the case of our responses to music is whether the formal composition of the work—in this case, the syntactic features of compositions that constitute a musical language is adequate for the attribution of the aesthetic feature in question. And this, Dickie argues, is a matter of convention rather than psychological causation—a matter of the rules of the particular language game appropriate to the production and appreciation of the category of music used as the stimulus. Questions about the nature of art and the character of aesthetic experience are prior logical questions about the use of a language.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Refute to Dickie’s arguments: recent imaging studies involving adjective matching and preference orderings support Dickie’s observations but challenge his assessment of the relevance of psychology to aesthetics: correlations among Calvo-Merino’ imaging results revealed common cortical networks subserving participants’ aesthetic judgments. Discussions of the functions of these cortical networks suggest that aesthetic judgments within a medium are realized by a unique set of psychological processes.
<ul>
<li>one can argue against Dickie that our use of aesthetic concepts in ordinary language draws on, reflects, or perhaps even itself constitutes an underlying tacit theory about the nature of art and the character of aesthetic experience; our systematic use of aesthetic terms in ordinary language should yield testable predictions about the nature of art and the character of aesthetic experience. Therefore, even if, as Dickie suggests, the philosopher of art is concerned with language games, a language game can be studied empirically.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>In below, the essay explores significant interactions between philosophy and psychology with special regard to the arts of literature, music, and visual art.</p>
<h2 id="literature">Literature</h2>
<ul>
<li>Jenefer Robinson’s Deeper than Reason: The Emotions and their Role in Literature, Music and Art.
<ul>
<li>James’s approach to the emotions: it is physiological change that is essential to an emotion. When we perceive something that causes fear, for example, that perception directly causes bodily changes.</li>
<li>judgmentalism: A judgment is an assertion and an assertion entails that we believe its propositional content. Therefore, the judmentalist holds that in order for an emotion to take hold, it is necessary that we have certain beliefs: an emotional state is essentially a judgment.</li>
<li>Robinson&rsquo;s rejection to the judgmentalism:
<ul>
<li>thought experiments (philosophically)
<ul>
<li>imagining cutting finger in half: emotion happens without belief</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>psychological
<ul>
<li>Zajonc has demonstrated that, at least in primitive episodes of emotional response such as the startle reaction, affect can obtain without being caused by any cognitive state</li>
<li>Zajonc and his colleagues have established that people form preferences for stimuli to which they had been previously exposed, but that were presented to them at rates too fast to allow conscious recognition</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>neuroscience
<ul>
<li>Joseph LeDoux: &ldquo;Thinking, fast and slow&rdquo;: &ldquo;fast&rdquo; activates the amygdala directly, but then that system is checked by processes operating in the frontal cortex (&ldquo;slow&rdquo;).</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>On the judgmentalist picture, the emotional state begins with a conscious <em>judgment</em>—an evaluation or appraisal of the stimuli: this causes a <em>feeling</em> state in me that puts me on the lookout for more relevant information and primes my <em>behavioral</em> response.</p>
<p>For Robinson, perception -&gt; physiological -&gt; behavioral -&gt; cognition kicks in at this point in the process, monitoring the earlier stages of the process and either endorsing them or modifying them. Robinson believes that changes in the facial musculature and the corresponding alterations of the autonomic nervous system provide some grounds for discriminating between the so-called basic emotions (e.g., anger, disgust, fear, joy, sadness, and surprise). However, she also maintains, as do the judgmentalists, that it is primarily the cognitive processing that attends the emotion that fixes the identity of the affective state.</p>
<p>However, some emotions look like they require a lot of cognition in the form of some antecedent deliberation. Absorbing literature emotionally seems more like the sort of affect that is born of reflection than like a non-cognitive reflex such as the startle response.</p>
<p>Reading a fiction prompts our memory system to recall event types like the ones in the story that provoke immediate, non-cognitive, affective appraisals, and thereby activate physiological changes and behavioral tendencies; this then is cognitively monitored, leading to an adjustment of our appraisal of the situation, refining our understanding of it.</p>
<ul>
<li>cognitively monitoring our emotional responses to literature can provide the foundation of our interpretive response</li>
</ul>
<p>=&gt; Therefore, psychology is anything but irrelevant to the philosophy of art: it both contributes to our understanding of and enhances our capacity for narrative appreciation.</p>
<h2 id="music">Music</h2>
<ul>
<li>Plato&rsquo;s Republic: music in different modes affects our mental states in different ways
<ul>
<li>music is something we make direct physical contact with; the emotional and aesthetic effects of music are directly caused by the physical properties of musical sounds.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Eduard Hanslick’s The Beautiful in Music.
<ul>
<li>our affective responses to music could not involve genuine emotions, for an emotional response is not possible unless its object has some semantic content.
<ul>
<li>similar to judgementalist</li>
<li>in order for us to be saddened by music, the music would have to depict some particular thing that we recognize and react to in a canonical way. But music does not have the semantic resources of a language.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Similarly, Peter Kivy
<ul>
<li>The inability of music to express emotion literally is a conceptual claim for Kivy—it ultimately rests on our definition of the nature of emotion and the nature of music. Philosophers would do well to recognize that although questions about the nature of music or emotions may be partly conceptual questions, they are also <strong>empirical questions</strong>. Indeed, even where they are conceptual questions, our concepts continue to evolve as they are influenced by scientific developments.
<ul>
<li>the study of subject and object: perceptual psychology, the science of acoustics, affective neuroscience, cognition, emotion</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="music-imagery">Music Imagery</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Wittgenstein, Ryle, and Scruton: imagining is simply an attitude we take. Rather than believing that we hear a melody when there is no actual sound present, we merely imagine the sound.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>“imagination” is currently used to refer to any one of several related concepts:</p>
<ul>
<li>imagination as the production of mental imagery</li>
<li>imagination as a faculty that organizes percepts for coherent cognition (the constructive imagination)
<ul>
<li>Kant argues that the imagination is responsible for shaping sensory information from perception so that it is available to our understanding, or coherent to us.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>imagination in the sense of being imaginative or creative</li>
<li>imagination as a propositional attitude taken towards fictional or imaginary propositions.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>Hume’s A Treatise of Human Nature: the imagination is a storehouse of ideas derived from past perceptions
=&gt; Cognition is a capacity that always needs the imagination, since it involves the comparison of present perceptions to past perceptions, or the application of general concepts, which are formed by the imagination. Having an image of something not present also involves the imagination, since this involves either the recall of a past idea from the imagination, or the construction of a new idea out of past ideas. To be imaginative in the sense of being creative, then, is to be especially innovative in constructing new ideas, whether these ideas are imagistic (i.e., sensory) or abstract.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Visual imagery has dominated mental imagery research in the late 20th century. These studies have demonstrated that imagery preserves key metrical properties of perceptual representations in a target modality, that it draws on the same neurophysiological processes as perception in a target modality, and that the capacity for imagery is disrupted by both focal damage and the application of repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) to the discrete brain regions that realize these perceptual processes.</p>
<ul>
<li>Kosslyn, Ball, and Reiser: differences in the time it takes to answer questions about the presence of targets on a <em>memorized</em> map are proportional to the distances one would have to scan to locate them on the original.</li>
<li>Shepard and Metzler: differences in the time it takes for participants to evaluate whether an object is identical to a target in mental rotation studies are proportional to the distance the former would have to be rotated to match the latter.</li>
<li>imaging studies demonstrate that visual imagery tasks employ the same areas of the cerebral cortex that are involved in ordinary perception</li>
<li>Bisiach and Luzzatti: selective damage to one side of the cerebral cortex causes patients to fail to perceive objects in associated areas of the visual field, generalize to visual imagery.</li>
<li>Kosslyn and his colleagues have demonstrated that the use of rTMS to disrupt activity in areas of the cerebral cortex involved in the encoding of sensory information in visual experience also disrupts the capacity in normal perceivers to use imagery and visualization to make spatial comparisons among the parts of recollected visual stimuli</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>Auditory imagery experiments confirm that the metric properties (pitch, rhythm, and timbre) of auditory perception are preserved in auditory imagery: auditory imagery draws on the same neurophysiological processes in the auditory cortex as ordinary hearing, and that focal damage to these areas disrupts auditory imagery.</p>
<ul>
<li>Halpern: asked participants to identify whether a lyric was part of a song or not. Those asked to mentally play through the song took longer to respond than those who were not, and differences in their response times were proportional to the musical time between the target lyrics</li>
<li>In a second experiment, Halpern asked participants to identify whether a note corresponding to a lyric was higher or lower in pitch than the starting note. Some subjects could not do this at all. However, those with musical training were better than non-musicians, and differences in response times were more pronounced than in
the previous experiment.</li>
<li>the evidence seems to point towards a representation that
<ul>
<li>codes extension in time</li>
<li>unfolds in real time</li>
<li>has strong links between adjacent element</li>
<li>unidirectionally ordered</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>Overall, these studies in psychology and neuroscience support the hypothesis that “parts of the cortex specialized for processing actual sound are also recruited to process imagined sound.” This, in turn, lends support for the phenomenological intuition that the experience of imagery is importantly like the experience of perception.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Auditory memories seem to be stored as past auditory percepts, and can be recalled in a way that reproduces the pitch and temporal details of the original auditory experience.</p>
<ul>
<li>Zatorre and Halpern review evidence that suggests that it is plausible to think that composers who report “hearing” their compositions internally are drawing on the same capacity for auditory imagery used to rehearse a remembered piece of music. Hearing a piece that one already knows involves reviving an auditory image of that piece, drawing upon memory stores that function as a kind of constructive imagination.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>neural underpinnings of auditory imagery elucidates an important component of the musical listening experience</p>
<ul>
<li>musical capacities are highly variable: both listening to and performing music seems to alter the very structure of the brain - arguably, what is happening is the formation of <strong>aural/musical categories</strong> for the components of music as well as for entire compositions.
<ul>
<li>2 possibilities:
<ul>
<li>musical ability relevant to music listening can be developed later in life</li>
<li>there are limits to what listening capacities many people can develop</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="visual-art">Visual art</h2>
<p>Cogintive Science: is the study of the way organisms acquire, recognize, manipulate, and use information in the production of behavior (the input and the output and their relationship): perceptual, affective, and cognitive</p>
<p>Current research in the cognitive neuroscience of visual art lies at the confluence of two broad research strategies:</p>
<ul>
<li>empirical aesthetics: examine behavioral responses to artworks.</li>
<li>aesthetic experimentalism: the view that visual artists develop formal and compositional vocabularies by trial and error, or through a systematic exploration of the perceptual effects of different sets of marks, color schemes, and compositional arrangements. Therefore, we can learn about the operations of perceptual systems by examining the productive strategies of artists</li>
</ul>
<p>cognitive neuroscience of visual art rests on the assumption that correlations between the <strong>formal features of artworks</strong> and basic <strong>neurophysiological</strong> mechanisms in the visual system can be used to explain how visual artworks work as perceptual stimuli. A good deal of research in the cognitive neuroscience of visual art is dedicated to searching out and explaining these relationships between the formal strategies employed by artists and the operations of the visual system.</p>
<ul>
<li>visual system is a set of evolved biological mechanisms whose function is to select information from sensory inputs that is sufficient for visual recognition and action</li>
<li>The input to the visual system is replete with information about the local environment. However, only a small fraction of this information is diagnostic for the identity of an object, action, or event at any given time.</li>
<li>Artists’ formal methods and vocabularies are tools for selecting features sufficient for object, action, and event recognition from ordinary perceptual experience and rendering them in a medium</li>
</ul>
<p>Artworks can be thought of as artifacts intentionally designed to direct attention (perceptually sailent) to their artistically salient features (perceptual features responsible for the aesthetic effects and semantic associations)</p>
<h3 id="3-case-studies">3 case studies</h3>
<h4 id="georges-seurats-bathers-at-asnières">Georges Seurat’s Bathers at Asnières</h4>
<p>Georges Seurat used a formal technique called irradiation to enhance edges and amplify figure–ground segregation in Bathers at Asnières</p>
<ul>
<li>Irradiation is derived from the observation of Mach bands in ordinary perception, but has been used by painters long ago.
<ul>
<li>Mach band: Lateral inhibition helps boost the perception of object edges
<ul>
<li>A ganglion cell in the retina receives excitatory signals from photoreceptors and inhibitory signals from other ganglion cells that surround it. Ganglion cells along the bright side of the border between these regions receive less inhibition from their neighbors on the dark side. The overall response of these cells will therefore be higher than their neighbors</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>one function of lateral inhibition is to amplify the intensity of a feature of the sensory input that defines the boundaries between objects in perception. This in turn contributes to form recognition by enhancing the contrast between figure and ground, thereby sharpening the perception of depth in the picture plane.</p>
<p>An artists’ formal vocabulary =&gt; its utility in paintings is explained by neurophysiological mechanisms in the visual system.</p>
<p>However, although this case study demonstrates that cognitive neuroscience can contribute to our understanding of the way paintings work as perceptual stimuli, it does not establish irradiated edges as <strong>artistically salient</strong> features of Bathers at Asnières, because Mach band is everywhere in the real life but we do not find all of them aesthetically pleasing =&gt; if the nature of art can be explained in terms of ordinary psychological processes subserving our engagement with artworks, one needs an additional explanation to determine what, if anything, differentiates artworks from ordinary artifacts.</p>
<h3 id="mona-lisa">Mona Lisa</h3>
<p>Sfumato is a formal technique in which artists blur the sharp edges that define object features in a painting. Leonardo used this technique to render the critical facial features that define Mona Lisa’s expression, the corners of her mouth and eyes. Gombrich argues that these sfumato contours introduce a degree of ambiguity into the painting that forces viewers to use their imagination to interpret an expression that cannot ever be discretely resolved.</p>
<ul>
<li>Livingstone has demonstrated that differences between the spatial resolution of peripheral and foveal vision explain how sfumato works to generate the dynamics of Mona Lisa’s expression
<ul>
<li>We are able to discern remarkably fine-grained visual detail in the central, or foveal, region of the visual field, but nearly blind to visual features defined by coarse-grained visual information; converse is true for peripheral vision. Livingstone reports that the spatial resolution of normal vision diminishes by a factor of 10 just 7 degrees from the central.
<ul>
<li>This difference in spatial resolution between central, or foveal, and peripheral vision is explained by the fact that the receptive fields of peripheral retinal neurons are dramatically larger than those of their foveal counterparts: foveal neurons are sensitive to sharp, narrow-luminance boundaries that carry high-spatial-frequency information, but are unable to register coarse, broad-luminance gradients, like contours rendered in sfumato, that carry low- and medium-spatial-frequency information.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Smile is &ldquo;represented&rdquo; using sfumato in low and medium spatial frequencies: when one foveates on Mona Lisa’s smile it disappears; the smile reappears in a viewer’s peripheral field when he or she looks away.</p>
<p>Gombrich VS Livingstone:</p>
<ul>
<li>Gombrich: a viewer’s interpretation of Mona Lisa’s expression should vary with his or her state of mind</li>
<li>Livingstone: he depicted expression varies systematically with the distance of one’s focus of attention from the center of Mona Lisa’s face</li>
</ul>
<p>However, similarly, it does not establish sfumatoed smile as <strong>artistically salient</strong> feature because of the same reason.
Nonetheless, Livingstone’s discussion contributes evidence in support of a particular hypothesis about the aesthetic quality of the painting.</p>
<p>Theories about the nature of art and aesthetic experience rest ultimately on their <strong>consistency</strong> with facts about the way we engage with particular artworks =&gt; vision science, or psychology in general can serve as constraints to help decide among competing theories.</p>
<h3 id="slave-market-with-the-disappearing-bust-of-voltaire">Slave Market with the Disappearing Bust of Voltaire</h3>
<p>Dalí’s painting is a bistable ambiguous image (like the duck/rabbit image). The bistability is an artistically salient feature of the painting that generates both the perceptual ambiguity and the range of semantic associations that are constitutive of its identity as an artwork.</p>
<p>Bonnar and her colleagues used a technique called <strong>frequency-specific</strong> adaptation to demonstrate that this high- and low-spatial-frequency information was selectively used to drive the perception of either the nuns or the bust of Voltaire in the painting.</p>
<ul>
<li>the nuns were more apparent in the high-spatial-frequency images and the bust of Voltaire was more apparent in the low-spatial-frequency images.</li>
<li>hypothesis: Frequency-specific adaptation can be used to desensitize the visual system to the particular spatial-frequency information presented in a stimulus. participants adapted to high-spatial-frequency information should see the bust of Voltaire and participants adapted to low-spatial-frequency information should see the two nuns.</li>
<li>Participants were primed with either high- (first group) or low-spatial-frequency (2nd group) dynamic noise. THe first group reported seeing Voltaire; the 2nd saw nuns.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="summary">Summary</h3>
<p>We can come to understand the nature of art and aesthetic experience by tracking the relationship between the formal and compositional structure of particular artworks and viewers’ behavioral responses.</p>
<p>The model that emerges defines artworks as attentional strategies intentionally designed to direct attention and enhance the perception of features diagnostic for their artistically salient aesthetic (e.g., Mona Lisa’s elusive smile) and semantic (e.g., the bistable ambiguous content of Dalí’s painting) content.</p>
<p>These case studies each demonstrate a role for exogenous, stimulus-driven attentional processes in our engagement with artworks. However, attention is also <strong>endogenously</strong> driven by knowledge and expectations. Research suggests that artworks are attentional strategies that harness both basic formal features and viewers’ semantic knowledge, including art historical knowledge of the unique sets of formal strategies used to categorize artworks as belonging to artistic types (e.g., the works of particular artists, schools, or epochs), to convey their content.</p>
<h2 id="challenges">Challenges</h2>
<ul>
<li>more work needs to be done to determine how to <strong>isolate and model</strong> the types of aesthetic and semantic effects used to categorize artifacts as artworks.</li>
<li>one needs a way to constrain our understanding of formal structure to just those features and relations that contribute to the function of an artifact as an artwork.
<ul>
<li>functional rather than descriptive</li>
<li>the functional sense provides a principled means not only to recover the content of the work without demanding explicit prior knowledge of an artist’s actual intentions, but also to evaluate the adequacy of competing interpretations of those intentions.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Toward a Science of Aesthetics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/2023/07/toward-a-science-of-aesthetics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jul 2023 11:39:15 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/2023/07/toward-a-science-of-aesthetics/</guid>
      <description>A Paper a Day: Toward a Science of Aesthetics by Arthur P. Shimamura</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1 id="toward-a-science-of-aesthetics-issues-and-ideas">Toward a Science of Aesthetics: Issues and Ideas</h1>
<ul>
<li>The opening chapter of the book <em>Aesthetics of Science</em> by Arthur P.Shimamura
<ul>
<li>draws on ideas, identifies issues in aesthetics science from philosophy, psychology, and neuroscience.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="problem-space-what-is-aesthetics">Problem Space: what is aesthetics</h2>
<ul>
<li>aesthetics when it was coined by Alexander Baumgarten: the study of how to mind beholds beautiful objects
<ul>
<li>aesthetic response/experience: feelings of beauty; certain physical properties of an object may evoke it, but the experience itself is purely subjective.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Now: all kinds of <em>hedonic</em> response (a preference judgment) to a sensory experience
<ul>
<li>all kinds of emotion: beauty, anger, horror (emotion)</li>
<li>pique sensory processes (perception)</li>
<li>new idea, past experience (conception)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Who: beholder&rsquo;s experience, not artist&rsquo;s. Highlight the ways in which art is perceived, interpreted (conceptual), and felt (emotional).</li>
<li>object of interest: art (some art may be anti-aesthetic), natural phenomena, objects not intended to be art</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="philosophical-4-approaches-that-highlights-different-aspects-of-human-psychological-experiences">Philosophical: 4 approaches that highlights different aspects of human psychological experiences</h2>
<h3 id="mimetic-an-imitation-of-the-real-world">Mimetic: an imitation of the real world</h3>
<p>Plato: art is at best a twice removal from the ideal world
Aristotle: art could rarify essential univerals
In paintings, artists create the illusion of objects in 3-D space on a 2-D surface , a feat that requires the knowledge of reverse-engineering the human vision.</p>
<ul>
<li>linear perspective and chiaroscuro</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="expressionist-express-and-induce-emotions">Expressionist: express and induce emotions</h3>
<ul>
<li>Francis Hutcheson: feelings of beauty and pleasure, independent of the object&rsquo;s purpose or function; subjective feelings but there are absolute standards.</li>
<li>David Hume: beauty is purely subjective (taste), because it is not in objects themselves. But there is universal standards on taste.</li>
<li>Kant: We interpret the world by linking sensory experience to pre-existing concepts or ideas (cognitive approach).
<ul>
<li>judgments of taste =&gt; decide what gives us pleasureable feelings</li>
<li>features of objects that are pleasureable: agreeable, good, and beautiful. Aesthetic judgements are judgments/evaluations of beautiful things</li>
<li>beauty: innate idea, a universal concept =&gt; Aesthetic judgments are both subjective (experience) and universal (innate, universal concept of beauty)</li>
<li>sublime: not a proeprty of an object, it is a feeling to be elicited.</li>
<li>aesthetic judgments are not associated with an object’s function or purpose: disinterested =&gt; art for art&rsquo;s sake, Romanticism</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="formalist-abstract-the-sensory-quality">Formalist: abstract the sensory quality</h3>
<ul>
<li>Clement Greenberg about painting: 2-D is 2-D, not an illusion of 3-D. Impressionism.</li>
<li>Clive Bell: the essence of the aesthetic experience as per- ceiving significant <em>form</em>. The beholder considers an artwork purely on the basis of sensory features—that is, the aesthetic interplay of colors, lines, textures, and shapes: content and objects in a painting are irrelevant.</li>
<li>The advent of photographs moved artist away from mimetic and expressionist approaches to a formalist approach.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="conceptual-convey-a-concept">Conceptual: convey a concept</h3>
<ul>
<li>prehistory art: convey a message, often to a higher being.</li>
<li>post-modernism: meta-art: try to explore the nature/meaning of art
<ul>
<li>ex: Duchamp&rsquo;s <em>Fountain</em></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>requires knowledge about the symbolic referents displayed in an artwork. To appreciate meta-art statements, it is necessary to have knowledge about art history and the various ways art has been defined.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="summarization-of-philosophical-approaches">Summarization of Philosophical approaches</h3>
<p>Each of these approaches highlights different aspects of the beholder’s mental processes involved in the art experience: sensory processes with mimetic and formalist approaches, emotional processes with an expressionist approach, and semantic or cognitive processes with a conceptual approach.</p>
<h2 id="empirical-approaches-psychological-science">Empirical Approaches: Psychological Science</h2>
<h3 id="perception">Perception</h3>
<ul>
<li>Gustav Fechner, 1860: Psychophysics: the ways in which physical stimuli are registered by the mind.
<ul>
<li>Fechner, 1876: psychophysics of aesthetics. He suggested that aesthetics could be studied from the bottom up (elemental perceptual features): preference judgments for basic shapes, colors.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Gestalt psychology, early 20th century: perceptions could not be dissected into basic elements. It is the organization of a visual scene that we interpret and not the elemental features; the principle of Prägnanz, the notion that we organize our perceptions based on the simplest or most succinct interpretations.
<ul>
<li>Rudolf Arnheim applied Gestalt principles to the study of visual aesthetics. His Gestaltist interpretations stressed the manner in which the organization and dynamics of perceptual features act to create interest- ing works of art. He described paintings with respect to the “perceptual forces” that artists induced through balance, harmony, and object placement, anf these forces give rise to aesthetic experiences, such as a sense of calm or tenseness.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="emotion">Emotion</h3>
<p>Daniel Berlyne:</p>
<ul>
<li>optimally pleasing artworks are those that create some arousal or psychological tension but not so much that they become disturbing.</li>
<li>arousal is determined by specific features of artworks, such as novelty, complexity, surprisingness, uncertainty, and incongruity: they must work together to produce emotion, the greater the nuumber of those features, the greater the arousal.
<ul>
<li>the features are not properties of the object, but related to the beholder’s past experience and knowledge.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="empirical-approaches-cognitive-science">Empirical Approaches: Cognitive Science</h2>
<ul>
<li>draws heavily on computer-based models of how the mind works.</li>
<li>information processing approach: the way sensory signals act as information that is encoded, interpreted, represented, and stored.
<ul>
<li>bottom up: from sensory signals to knowledge
<ul>
<li>Gustav Fechner</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>top down: the use of knowledge to direct what we perceive (knowing is seeing, conceptual)
<ul>
<li>Ernst Gombrich
<ul>
<li>Based on our personal and cultural knowledge, the beholder forms expectations that help interpret an artwork and direct viewing to salient features</li>
<li>All art is illusory and we must build an interpretation of what an artwork represents based on existing knowledge (Schema): art as symbols</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="empirical-approaches-neuroscience">Empirical Approaches: Neuroscience</h2>
<p>Neuroscientists have studied the workings of the brain from many levels of analysis—from analyses of individual brain cells (i.e., neurons) to the study of neural activity in the human brain. Both structural (anatomical) and functional (brain activity) analyses have been used to investigate the neural correlates of human cognitive function.</p>
<ul>
<li>Example: Prefrontal cortex (PFC): It receives inputs from other brain regions and sends projections back to these regions. In this way, the PFC coordinates and controls neural processing: top down processing</li>
<li>Korbinian Brodmann, 1909: defined 52 distinct areas in cerebral cortex on the basis of physical features, such as size, shape, and density (Brodmann areas).</li>
<li>Neuropsychological: the study of the relationship between behavior, emotion, and cognition on the one hand, and brain function on the other
<ul>
<li>observing the way damage to different parts of the brain disrupts cognitive function
<ul>
<li>case of Phineas Gage</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Neuroimaging: fMRI: neuroscientists can assess brain activity in specific regions, virtually on a moment-to-moment basis
<ul>
<li>subtraction method: obtain scans from one condition and compare them to scans from another</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Neuroaesthetics
<ul>
<li>Kawabata and ZekiL: Neural correlates of beauty: The orbitofrontal cortex was active when subjects were presented with paintings that they rated as beautiful compared to those rated as neutral.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="issues-for-aesthetic-science">Issues for Aesthetic Science</h2>
<p>Philosophical approaches offer guidelines for scientific investigations of aesthetics.</p>
<ul>
<li>mimetic, formalist: perceptual</li>
<li>expressionist: emotion</li>
<li>few empirical studies have addressed conceptual approaches to art, studying the role of knowledge in our art experience</li>
</ul>
<p>beholder: sensation, knowledge, and emotion (SKE)</p>
<p>artist: intention (I)
=&gt; I-SKE framework</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>