<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>ravel on Wenxuan Zhao</title>
    <link>https://allanware.github.io/tags/ravel/</link>
    <description>Recent content in ravel on Wenxuan Zhao</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Jun 2022 18:32:37 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://allanware.github.io/tags/ravel/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>When you wake up from a bad dream</title>
      <link>https://allanware.github.io/posts/2022/06/when-you-wake-up-from-a-bad-dream/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jun 2022 18:32:37 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://allanware.github.io/posts/2022/06/when-you-wake-up-from-a-bad-dream/</guid>
      <description>Daphne and Chloe Ravel&amp;rsquo;s largest work, the only ballet work, commissioned by Sergei Diaghilev Ballets Russes
Harmony &amp;amp; orchestration, to achieve the dreamy effect, 他梦中的古希腊
the story In Lesbos, Daphnis and Chloe are in love with each other. But pirates one day came and abducted Chloe. Daphnis anguished and fainted before the statue of Nymphs. The Nymphs called Pan and they rescued Chloe from the pirates and bring her back to Daphnis.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="daphne-and-chloe">Daphne and Chloe</h2>
<p>Ravel&rsquo;s largest work, the only ballet work, commissioned by Sergei Diaghilev Ballets Russes</p>
<p>Harmony &amp; orchestration, to achieve the dreamy effect, 他梦中的古希腊</p>
<h3 id="the-story">the story</h3>
<p>In Lesbos, Daphnis and Chloe are in love with each other. But pirates one day came and abducted Chloe. Daphnis anguished and fainted before the statue of Nymphs. The Nymphs called Pan and they rescued Chloe from the pirates and bring her back to Daphnis.</p>
<h3 id="the-music">The music</h3>
<p>in the beginning, starting from A, it layers perfect 5th on top of the previous ones =&gt; hard to figure out the tonic &amp; the layers create a sense of levitation &amp; create a dreamy world. In the end, the starting A becomes D sharp. Incidentally, it forms a tritone (3 whole steps, 6 half steps, augmented fourth, the so-called devil&rsquo;s interval, a dissonance)</p>
<p>The D-sharp is then connected to and becomes the beginning of the <em>Theme of the Nonhuman World</em> (Pan and three Nymphs), a free flute melody (非常空灵，彷佛就是不属于人间之物). then the melody transits to a french horn melody, that is &ldquo;concrete&rdquo; in rhythm and harmony, which is the <em>Theme of Daphnis and Chloe</em>. Inside the theme, there is a downward perfect 5th and an upward perfect 5th (which may each represent one of the twos).</p>
<p>Another 2 notable themes: <em>Sad Waltz</em>, <em>The Pirates</em>(played by french horn and trumpets). The themes are played together in some scenes, an example of which is when the pirates came and abducted Chloe: the pirates theme, followed by the theme of Daphnis and Chloe, and then the sad waltz to represent Chloe&rsquo;s agitation, and then the pirates theme, and then the first half (only the part that represents Daphnis) of the theme of Daphnis and Chloe is repeated. When Daphnis is so sad that he falls into a coma, it enters the theme of the nonhuman world, with the background using the muted strings. The melodies that represent three nymphs show up one by one (flute melody), each of them starting with tones played by harp and celesta that signifies the appearance of something non-human.</p>
<p>Part II starts from a scene in the Pirates&rsquo; camp, the Pirates theme is played</p>
<p>Daphnis et Chloe Suite No. 1: a suite that starts from the entry of 3 nymphs (in the first part) and ends at 海盗战舞 that plays the Pirates theme.</p>
<p>Daphnis et Chloe Suite No. 2: includes the whole part III. It starts from Daybreak, when Pan rescues Chloe and brings her back to Daphnis when he starts to recover from the bad dream: flute, clarinet, celesta, and harp portray 海边初晓（因为故事发生的地点在细浪一个岛上）的波光粼粼。piccolo and strings that imitates bird songs that signify the coming of a new day and anything bad will end. After that 一段非常美好的段落 （因为牧羊人小伙伴们发现chloe回来了），然后他们四处寻找dalphnis，接着一个 Tristan Chord （激动，因为找到了昏迷在地的达芙妮）, then a sad waltz that sounds agitated, then we finally again hear the complete version of the theme of the Daphnis and Chloe.</p>
<p>On June 3rd, CSO will play the whole thing, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daphnis_et_Chlo%C3%A9"><em>Daphnis and Chloe, Choreographic Symphony in Three Parts</em></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>